you
Krishnamurti in dialogue with Dr. Alan W. Anderson.
J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England.
For the past 40 years, he
has been speaking in the United States,
Europe, India, Australia, and other parts of the world.
From the outset of his life's work,
he repudiated all connections
with organized religions and ideologies
and said that his only concern
was to set men absolutely unconditionally free.
He is the author of many books, among them
The Awakening of Intelligence, The Urgency of Change,
Freedom from the Known, and The Flight of the Eagle.
This is one of a series of
dialogues between Krishnamurti and Dr. Alan W. Anderson,
who is professor of religious studies at
San Diego University.
Dr. Anderson is a professor at San Diego State University,
where he teaches Indian and
Chinese scriptures and the oracular tradition.
Dr. Anderson, a published poet,
received his degree from Columbia University
and the Union Theological Seminary.
He has been honored with a Distinguished Teaching Award
from the California State Universities.
Mr. Krishnamurti, just at the point where
we left last time in our conversation,
we had raised the question of the distinction between
the notion that I must be responsible for my action
and just being responsible.
That's it.
I was sitting here thinking to myself,
oh, why can't we go on?
So perhaps we could start at that point.
Would that be agreeable?
I think, sir, there is a very definite distinction
between responsible for and being responsible.
If I...
Being responsible for implies a direction.
えー
a directed will.
But the feeling of responsibility
implies responsibility for everything,
not in a direction, in any one particular direction.
Responsible for education, responsible for politics,
responsible for the way I
live, responsible for my behaviour,
it's a total feeling of complete responsibility,
which is the ground in which action takes place.
I think then this takes us
back to this business of crisis
we were talking about.
If the crisis is continuous, then it's misleading to say,
I'm responsible for my action,
because I've put the thing out there again,
and it becomes an occasion for
my confusing what is at hand
that requires to be done,
and the concept of this notion of my action,
because I am my action.
Yes, that's it. I am it.
That means I am...
The feeling of responsibility expresses itself
politically,
religiously, educationally, in business,
in the whole of life,
responsible for the total behaviour,
not in a particular direction.
I think there is a great deal of difference.
When one says, I am responsible for my action,
that means you are responsible for your action
according to the idea that
you have preconceived about action.
Exactly. Yes.
People sometimes will say that the child is free
because it's not responsible.
Oh, child is...
You can't take a child...
No, of course not.
But I think sometimes when we say this,
we have this nostalgia for the past,
as though our freedom would be freedom from constraint.
Whereas if one is his action genuinely, absolutely...
There is no restraint.
There isn't any restraint at all.
None at all. Right.
Because, sir, look, if one is totally...
has this total feeling of responsibility,
then what is your responsibility?
You have to have a
responsibility with regard to your children.
That means education.
Are you educating them to bring about a mind
that conforms to the pattern
which the society has established?
Which means you accept the
immorality of the society that is.
Uh-huh.
Totally responsible you are.
Responsible from the moment it's
born till the moment it dies.
The right kind of education,
not the education of making the child conform,
and the worship of success,
and the division of nationalities which brings about war.
You follow? All that you are responsible for.
Not just in a particular direction.
Even if you are in a particular direction,
I am responsible for my act,
what is your action based on?
How can you be responsible
when your action is the result of a formula
that has been handed down to you?
Yes, I quite follow what you mean.
Like communists,
they are...
They say the state is responsible.
The state worships the state.
The state is the god.
And you are responsible to the state.
Which means they have conceived what the state should be,
formulated ideationally,
and according to that you act.
That is not responsible action.
That is irresponsible action.
Whereas action means the doing now,
the active present of the verb to do,
which is to do now, the acting now.
The acting now must be free from the past.
Otherwise you are just repeating, repetition.
Traditionally, adding on. That is not...
I am reminded of something in the I Ching
that I think is a reflection of this principle
that you pointed to.
I don't mean principle in the abstract.
If I am quoting it correctly
from one of the standard translations,
it goes like this,
the superior man, by which it means the superior,
the free man, not hierarchically structured,
does not let his thoughts go beyond his situation.
Which would mean that he simply
would be present as he is,
not being responsible to something out there
that is going to tell him how to be responsible,
what he should do.
But upon the instant that he is,
he is always...
Responsible.
He simply does not let
his thoughts go beyond his situation.
That goes back to that word negation.
Because if he won't let
his thoughts go beyond his situation,
he has negated the possibility
for their doing so, hasn't he?
Yes.
Oh yes, yes, yes, I see that.
The reason that I am referring to these
other quotations is because
if what you are saying is true,
and if what they say is true,
quite without respect to how they are understood
or not understood,
then there must be something in common here.
And I realize that your emphasis is on
practical, eminently practical, upon the act.
But it does seem to
me to be of great value
if one could converse, commune with the great literatures
which have so many statements in them
that complain about the fact that they are not understood.
I see that as a great gain.
So...
I have not read any books,
any literature in the sense...
Yes, sir, I understand.
...in that sense.
Suppose there is no book in the world.
Problem is the same.
Of course, of course.
There is no leader, no teacher,
nobody to tell you,
do this, do that, don't do this, don't do that.
You are there.
You feel totally, completely responsible.
Right. Yes.
Then you have to have an astonishingly active,
clear brain.
Not befuddled, not puzzled, not bewildered.
You must have a mind that thinks clearly,
clearly.
And you cannot think clearly
if you are rooted in the past.
You are merely continuing, modified perhaps,
through the present to the future.
That's all.
So, from that arises the question,
what is the responsibility in human relationship?
Yes, now we are back to relationship.
Relationship.
Because that is the basic foundation of life.
Relationship, that is to be related,
to be in contact with.
We are presently related.
This is what is.
Yes.
Now, what is human relationship?
If I feel totally responsible,
how does that responsibility express in relationship?
To my children, if I have children,
to my family, to my neighbour,
whether the neighbour is next door
or ten thousand miles away,
is still my neighbour.
So what is my responsibility?
What is the responsibility of a man
who feels totally,
completely involved in this feeling
of being a light to himself
and totally responsible?
I think this is a question, sir,
that has to be investigated,
which is not a question of the mind.
Yes, you know what I am thinking?
I am thinking that only a person responsible,
as you have said it,
can make what we call in our tongue
a clean decision.
Of course, of course.
So many decisions are frayed, are...
Sir, I would like to ask this.
Is there a decision at all?
Decision implies choice.
Yes.
Choice implies a mind that is confused
between this and that.
It means, I think, radically to make a cut,
to cut off.
Yes, but a mind that sees clearly has no choice.
It doesn't decide.
It acts.
Yes.
Doesn't this take us back to this word negation again?
Yes, of course.
Might it not be that a clean decision
could be interpreted in terms
of what takes place at this point of negation?
Yes.
From which flows a different action...
But I don't like to use that word decision.
Because the deciding between this and that...
You know, sir,
you don't want to use it because of
the implications in it of conflict.
Conflict.
I see, I see.
Choice.
We think we are free because we choose.
We can choose. Right?
Is a mind free that is capable of choice?
Or is a mind that is not free that chooses?
Choice implies between this and that.
Obviously.
Now, which means the mind doesn't see clearly
and therefore there is choice.
Choice exists when there is confusion.
Yes, yes, yes.
Mind that sees clearly, there is no choice.
It is doing.
I mean, I think that is...
I think this is where
we have got into rather trouble
when we say we are free to choose.
Choice implies freedom.
I say on the contrary.
Choice implies a mind that is confused
and therefore not free.
What occurs to me now is the difference between
regarding freedom,
as a property or quality of action,
rather than a state.
Oh!
Yes.
But we have the notion that freedom is a state,
a condition,
which is quite different from the emphasis
that you are leading me into.
Yes, that's right.
Yes, yes, yes.
So let's come back to this, I think, sir,
which is, what is the responsibility
of a human being
who feels free?
Who has this sense of responsibility in relationship?
Because relationship is life.
Relationship is the foundation of existence.
Relationship is absolutely necessary,
otherwise you can't exist.
Relationship means cooperation.
Everything is involved in that one word.
Relationship means love and generosity
and all that's implied.
Now, what is a human responsibility
in relationship?
If we were genuinely and completely sharing,
then responsibility would be present, fully.
Yes, but how does it express itself
in relationship?
Not only between you and me now,
but between man and woman,
between my neighbour,
between...
Relationship, sir, to everything, to nature.
What's my relationship to nature?
Would I go and kill the baby seals?
No, no.
Would I go and destroy human beings,
calling them enemies?
Would I destroy nature,
everything which man is doing now?
He is destroying the earth, the air, the sea, everything.
Because he feels totally irresponsible.
He sees what is out there
as something to operate on.
Yes, which is, he kills the baby seal,
which I saw the other day in a film,
which is an appalling thing.
And a Christian, they call themselves Christians,
going killing a little thing
for somebody's...
for some lady to put on the fur.
And you follow,
it's totally immoral, the whole thing is.
So, to come back, I say,
what is, how does this responsibility
show itself in my life?
I'm married.
I'm not, but suppose I'm married.
What is my responsibility?
Am I related to my wife?
The record doesn't seem very good.
No, not only record, actuality.
Am I related to my wife?
Or am I related to my wife
according to the image I have built about her?
And I'm responsible for that image.
You follow, sir?
Yes, because my input has been continuous
with respect to that image.
Yes. So, I have no relationship with my wife
if I have an image about her.
Or if I have an image about myself
when I want to be successful,
all the rest of that business.
Since we were talking about now,
being now,
there's a point of contact, I take it,
between what you're saying
and the phrase that you used
in one of our earlier conversations,
the betrayal of the present.
Absolutely.
Yes. If one...
You see, that is the whole point, sir.
If I am related to you,
I have no image about you
or you have an image about me.
Then we have relationship.
We have no relationship
if I have an image about myself
or about you.
Our images have a relationship.
But in actuality, we have no relationship.
I may sleep with my wife or with some,
but it is not a relationship.
It is a physical contact,
sensory excitement, nothing else.
So my responsibility is not to have an image.
This brings to mind,
I think, one of the loveliest statements
in the English language,
which I should like to understand
in terms of what we have been sharing.
These lines from Keats' poem, Endymion.
There's something miraculous, marvelous
in this statement, it seems to me,
that's immediately related
to what you've been saying.
A thing of beauty is a joy forever.
And then he says,
as though that's not enough,
he says, its loveliness increases.
Quite, quite.
And then as though that's not enough,
he says, it will never pass into nothingness.
Quite.
Now, when the present is not betrayed,
it's full with a fullness.
That keeps on abounding.
It's quite understandable.
Would I be correct in that?
Yes, I think so.
I think that's truly what he must be saying.
And one of the things,
too, that passed my mind was,
he calls it a thing of beauty.
He doesn't call it a beautiful thing.
No.
No, it's a thing of beauty,
as though it's a child of beauty.
Marvellous continuity between this.
Not it's beautiful
because I think it's beautiful,
and therefore it's outside.
This...
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
I must stick to this,
because this is really quite important.
Because you go where you will,
there is no relationship between human beings.
And that is the tragedy,
and from that arises the truth.
Because all our conflict, violence,
the whole business.
So, if...
No, not if.
When there is this responsibility,
the feeling of this responsibility,
it translates itself in relationship,
it doesn't matter with whom it is,
a freedom from the known,
which is the image.
And therefore, in that freedom,
goodness flowers.
Goodness flowers.
And that is the beauty.
And that is beauty.
Beauty is not an abstract thing,
but it goes with goodness.
Goodness in behaviour,
goodness in conduct,
goodness in action.
Sometimes while we've been talking,
I've started a sentence with, if...
Oh, yes.
And I've looked into your eyes,
and immediately I got it out,
I knew I'd said the wrong thing.
It's just like a minute ago,
you said if, and you said no, when.
Yes.
We are always if-ing it up.
I know, if-ing it up.
It is, it's awful.
I know, sir.
We are always dealing with abstractions
rather than with reality.
Immediately we if.
A construction is out there,
which we endlessly talk about.
That's right.
And we get cleverer and cleverer about it.
And it has nothing to do with anything.
Yes, yes, yes.
So, how does this responsibility
translate itself in human behaviour?
You follow, sir?
Uh-huh.
There would be an end to violence.
Absolutely.
Wouldn't taper off.
You see what we have done, sir?
We have taken...
We are violent human beings,
sexually, morally, in every way
we are violent human beings.
And not being able to resolve it,
we have created an ideal
of not being violent,
which is the fact
and abstraction of the fact,
which is non-fact,
and try to live the non-fact.
Yes.
Immediately that produces conflict
because it can't be done.
It produces conflict, misery, confusion,
all the rest of it.
Now, why does the mind do it?
The mind does it because
it doesn't know what to
do with this fact of violence.
Therefore, in abstracting,
the idea of not being violent
postpones action.
Uh-huh.
I am trying not to be violent.
And in the meantime, I am jolly well violent.
Yes.
And it is an escape from the fact.
All abstractions are escape from the fact.
So, the mind does it because
it is incapable of dealing with the fact,
or it doesn't want to deal with the fact,
or it is lazy and says,
well, I will try and do it some other day.
All those are involved
when it withdraws from the fact.
Now, in the same way,
the fact is,
our relationship is non-existent.
I may say to my wife,
I love you, I am, etc., etc.,
but it is non-existent.
Because I have an image about her
and she has an image about me.
So, on abstractions we have lived.
It just occurred to me that the word fact itself,
which there have been no end of disquisitions about...
Ah, of course.
Fact, what is, let's call it what is.
But actually it means something done.
Done, yes.
Not the record of something,
but actually something done, performed,
act, act.
And it is that sense of fact
that with our use of the word fact,
give me facts and figures,
we say in English, give me facts...
We don't mean that when we say it.
No.
No, no.
One probably wouldn't need facts and figures
in that abstract sense.
You see, sir, this reveals a tremendous lot...
I follow.
...when you feel responsible.
You feel responsible for education of your children.
Not only your children, children.
Are you educating them
to conform to a society
or are you educating them to merely acquire a job?
Are you educating them to
the continuity of what has been?
Are you educating them to live in abstractions,
as we are doing now?
So what is your responsibility
as a father, mother,
it doesn't matter who you are,
responsible in education,
for the education of a human being?
That's one problem.
What is your responsibility
if you feel responsible for human growth,
human culture, human goodness?
You?
What is your responsibility to the earth?
To nature? You follow?
It is a tremendous thing to feel responsible.
This just came to mind,
which I must ask you about.
The word negation in the book
that we looked at earlier,
which is continuous with what we are saying,
I think is itself rather endangered
by the usual notion that we have of negation,
which is simply a prohibition,
which is not meant.
No.
Which is not meant.
Of course.
When we reviewed that incident in the Gita
between the general and his charioteer,
the Lord Krishna,
the Lord's response was a negation
without it being a prohibition.
Quite, quite.
Wasn't it?
I don't know.
No, no, I mean in terms
of what we just got through seeing.
Yes, of course.
Yes.
There is a difference then between
rearing a child in terms of
relating to the child radically in the present,
in which negation, as is mentioned in the book here
that we went through,
is continuously
and immediately and actively present,
and simply walking around saying to oneself,
now I am rearing a child,
therefore I mustn't do these things,
and I mustn't do those things,
I must do that.
Exactly.
An entirely different thing.
But one has to break the habit
of seeing negation as prohibition.
And also, you see,
with responsibility goes love, care,
attention.
Yes, earlier I was going to ask you about care
in relation to responsibility.
Something that would flow immediately.
Naturally, sir.
Naturally, yes.
Not something that I would have to project
that I needed to care for later.
So I won't forget.
But I would be with it.
Yes.
That involves a great deal too,
because the mother,
the mother depends on the child,
and the child depends on the mother,
or the father, whatever it is.
So that dependence is cultivated,
not only between the father and the mother,
but depend on a teacher,
depend on somebody to tell you what to do,
depend on your guru.
Yes, yes, I am following.
So, gradually, the child, the man,
is incapable of standing alone.
And therefore you say,
I must depend on my wife
for my comfort, for my sex,
for my this or that and the other thing.
I am lost without her.
And I am lost without my guru,
without my teacher.
It becomes difficult.
It becomes so ridiculous.
So, when the feeling of responsibility exists,
all this disappears.
You are responsible
for your behaviour,
for the way you bring up your children,
for the way you treat a dog, a neighbour,
the nature,
everything is in your hands.
Therefore, you have to become astonishingly careful
what you do.
Careful, not,
I must not do this and I must do that.
Care.
That means affection,
that means consideration, diligence.
All that goes with responsibility,
which present society totally denies.
When we begin to discuss
the various gurus that are imported in this country,
that's what they are doing,
creating such mischief,
making those people unfortunate,
thoughtless people
who want excitement join them,
do all kinds of ridiculous, nonsensical things.
So, we come back.
Freedom implies responsibility.
And therefore freedom, responsibility
means care, diligence,
not negligence,
not doing what you want to do,
which is what is happening in America.
Do what you want to do.
This permissiveness is just doing what you want to do,
which is not freedom,
which breeds irresponsibility.
I met the other day in Delhi,
New Delhi, a girl,
and she has become reactivating.
You follow, sir?
Born in America, being a Christian,
brought up all that,
throws all that aside,
becomes a Tibetan,
which is the same thing in different words.
Yes, as a Tibetan coming over here and doing it.
It's all ridiculous.
And I've known her some years,
I said, where is your child?
Who is sick?
Oh, she says, I've left him
with other liberated Tibetans.
And I said,
at six, you are the mother?
She said, yes, sir,
he is in very good hands.
I come back next year and I ask,
where is your child?
Oh, he has become a Tibetan monk,
who is seven.
He is seven years old
and has become a Tibetan monk.
You understand, sir?
Oh, yes, I do.
The irresponsibility of it.
Because the mother feels
they know better than I do.
I have become, I am a Tibetan
and the lamas will help me to become that.
It puts a rather sinister cast
on that biblical statement,
train up a child in the way he should go,
and when he is old
he will not depart from it.
There is a sinister note in that, isn't there?
Absolutely.
So this is going on
in the world all the time.
And a man who is really serious,
negates that.
Because he understands the implications,
the inwardness of all that.
So he has to deny it.
It isn't a question of will or choice,
he says that is too silly, too absurd.
So freedom means responsibility
and indifference.
Infinite care.
نعم
The phrase that you just spoke, infinite care,
would be totally impossible to what
we mean by a finite being,
unless the finite being did not betray the present.
With not betraying the present, it's a negative again,
it's a negation again.
With not betraying the present,
which is not to say what
will happen if it's not done.
Sir, the word present, the now, is rather difficult.
Oh yes.
Philosophers love to call it the specious present.
I don't know what philosophers say,
I don't want to enter into all that speculative thinking.
But the fact, what is the now?
What is the act of now, the present?
To understand the present,
I must understand the past.
Not history, I don't mean that.
Understand myself as the past. I am the past.
In terms of what we said earlier about knowledge.
Yes, I am that.
Therefore I must understand the
present, the past, which is me.
The me is the known.
The me is not the unknown.
I can imagine it's the unknown,
but the me is the known.
Actually, the fact is, the what is, is the known.
That's me. I must understand myself.
If I don't, the now is merely
a continuation in modified form of the past.
Therefore it's not the now, not the present.
Therefore the me is the tradition, the knowledge,
the in...
all the complicated manoeuvres, cunning, you follow?
All that.
The despairs, the anxieties, the
desire for success, fear, pleasure,
all that is me.
Since we are still involved
in our discussion about relationship here,
might we return a moment to where we were
with respect to education and relationship?
I...
I want to be sure
that I have understood you here.
Let us say that one was
fortunate enough to have a school
where what you are pointing to was going on.
We are going to, we are doing it.
We have got several schools.
Marvellous.
Well, we'll have a chance
to talk about that, won't we?
Yes.
Good, good.
If I'm...
If I'm current here, it would seem
that if the teacher is totally present
to the child, the child will feel this.
The child won't have to be
instructed in what this means then.
Sir, that means...
Is that right?
Yes.
But one has to...
One has to find out what is
the relationship of the teacher to the student.
Yes. Yes, I quite see that. Of course.
What is the relationship?
Is he merely an informer,
giving information to the child?
Any machine can do that.
Oh yes, the library is filled with...
Any machine can.
Or what is his relationship?
Does he put himself on a pedestal up there,
and the student down there?
Yes.
Or is the relationship between the teacher and the student,
is it a relationship in which there is learning
on the part of the
teacher as well as the student?
Learning.
Yes.
Not, I have learnt and I'm going to teach you.
Therefore in that,
there is a division between the teacher and the student.
But when there is learning
on the part of the teacher
as well as on the part of the student,
there is no division, both are learning.
Yes.
And therefore that relationship
brings about a companionship.
A sharing.
A sharing, yes.
And taking a journey together.
And therefore an infinite care on both sides.
Uh-huh.
So it means, how is the teacher to teach mathematics,
or whatever it is, to the student,
and yet teach it in such a way
that you awaken the intelligence in the child,
not about the child,
but mathematics?
No, of course not. No. Yes.
And how do you bring this act of teaching
in which there is order?
Because mathematics means order.
The highest form of order is mathematics.
Now, how will you convey
to the student in teaching mathematics
that there should be order in his life?
Not order according to a blueprint,
that's not order.
You follow?
Yes, yes.
Therefore it's a creative teaching.
Not creative, it's a teaching,
an act of learning all the time.
So it's a living thing.
Uh-huh.
That's something I've learnt,
and I'm going to impart it to you.
This reminds me of a little essay
I read many years ago by Simone Weil,
which she called,
On Academic Studies.
There's some title like that.
And she said that every...
one who teaches a subject
is responsible for teaching the student
the relation between what they're studying
and the student's making a pure act of attention.
I know, of course.
And if this doesn't take place,
the whole thing doesn't mean a thing.
Sir, that just...
One stops to think,
what would a teacher say
if a student walked up and looked at them
and said, fine,
we're studying calculus right now.
Now, you tell me how I am to see this
that I am pursuing
in relation to my making
a pure act of attention.
Well, that would be likely a little embarrassing,
except for the most unusual person
who had this...
who had a grasp of the present.
Yes.
So, sir, that's just it.
What is the relationship of the teacher
to the student in education?
Is he training him merely to conform?
Is he training him to cultivate mere memory,
like a machine?
Is he training or is he helping him
to learn about life,
not just about sex,
life,
but about immensity of living,
the complexity of it?
Which we are not doing.
No.
No, even in our language
we refer students to subject matters.
Yes, yes, yes.
They take this, they take that,
they take the other,
and in fact there are prerequisites
for taking these other things.
And this builds a notion of education
which has absolutely no relationship
to what...
None at all.
And yet, amazingly,
in the catalogues of colleges and universities
across the country,
there is, in the first page or so,
a rather pious remark
about the relation between their going to school
and the values of civilisation.
And we have this whole...
And that turns out to be
learning a series of ideas.
I don't know whether they do it any more,
but they used to put the word
character in there.
They probably decided that's unpopular,
might very well have dropped that out by now,
I'm not sure.
Yes, yes, yes,
I'm following what you say.
So, sir,
when you feel responsible,
there is a flowering of real affection.
You understand, sir?
Mm-hm.
A flowering of care for a child.
And you don't train him
or cultivate or condition him
to go and kill another
for the sake of your country.
You follow?
All that is involved in it.
Mm-hm.
So,
we come to a point
where a human being,
as he is now,
so conditioned to be irresponsible,
how is that...
how...
what are the serious people
going to do with the irresponsible people?
You understand?
Mm-hm.
Education, politics, religion,
everything is making human beings irresponsible.
Mm-hm.
I'm not exaggerating, this is so.
Oh, no, you're not exaggerating, yes.
Now, I see this as a human being,
I say, what am I to do?
You follow, sir?
Mm-hm.
What is my responsibility
in face of the irresponsible?
Well, if it's to start anywhere,
as we say in English,
it must start at home.
It would have to start with me.
So I say, that's the whole point,
I have to start with me.
Right.
Then if from that question arises,
then you can't do anything about the irresponsible.
No, exactly.
No, sir.
Something strange takes place.
Oh, I misunderstood you, I'm sorry.
What I meant by replying there is
that I don't attack,
I attack the irresponsible.
No, no.
No, yes, go ahead. Yes.
Something strange takes place, which is,
consciousness,
the irresponsible consciousness is one thing.
Yes.
And the consciousness of responsibility is another.
Now, when the human being is totally responsible,
that responsibility unconsciously enters
into the irresponsible mind.
I don't know, I'm not saying anything.
Yes, no, no, no, go ahead.
Sir, look, I'm irresponsible.
Suppose I'm irresponsible.
You are responsible.
You can't do anything consciously with me.
Because the more you...
Because the more you actively operate on me,
the more I resist.
That's right. That's right.
That's what I meant by no attacking.
No attacking. I react violently to you.
I build a wall against you.
I hurt you. I do all kinds of things.
But you see that you cannot do anything consciously,
actively, let's put it that way.
Designedly.
Planned.
That's what they are all trying to do.
But if you can talk to me, to my unconscious...
Because the unconscious is much more active.
Oh, yes.
Much more alert, sees the danger much quicker
than the conscious.
So it's much more sensitive.
So if you can talk to me, to the unconscious,
that operates.
So you don't actively, designedly attack the irresponsible.
They have done it.
And they have made a mess of it.
Oh, yes, it compounds, complicates the thing further.
Whereas if you talk to him, you talk to me,
but your whole inward intention is to show
how irresponsible I am, what his responsibility means.
You follow?
You care.
In other words, you care for me.
Yes, yes.
I was chuckling because the complete and total opposite
crossed my mind, and it just seemed so absolutely absurd.
Yes.
No, I do.
You care for me because I am irresponsible.
You follow?
Exactly.
Therefore you care for me.
And therefore you are watching not to hurt me.
You follow?
In that way you penetrate very, very deeply
into my unconscious.
And that operates unknowingly when I am...
Suddenly I say, by Jove, how you are...
You follow?
That operates.
Uh-huh, uh-huh.
I have seen this, sir,
in operation, because I have talked for 50 years,
unfortunately or fortunately, to large audiences,
tremendous resistance to anything new.
Yes.
If I say, don't read sacred books,
which I say all the time,
because you are just conforming, obeying.
You are not living, you
are living according to some book
that you have read.
Immediately there is resistance.
Who are you to tell us?
Not to do something.
Not to do this or to do that.
So I say, all right, see,
I go on pointing out, pointing out.
I am not trying to change them.
I am not doing propaganda,
because I don't believe in propaganda, it is a lie.
So I say, look, look what
you do when you are irresponsible.
You are destroying your children.
You send them to war,
to be killed and to be
maimed and to kill and to maim.
It is that act of love, it
is that affection, it is that care.
Why do you do it?
And I go into it.
They get bewildered, they don't know what to do.
You know, sir?
So it begins to slowly seep in.
Well, at first it is such a shock.
It sounds positively subversive to some.
Oh, absolutely, absolutely subversive.
Of course, of course.
Yes, but...
So we enter into now something, which is,
my relationship to another,
when there is total responsibility
in which freedom and care go together,
I do not...
the mind has no image in relationship at all.
Because the image is the division.
Where there is care, there is no image, imagination,
no image.
This would lead us into
what perhaps later we could pursue,
love.
Ah, that's a tremendous thing.
Yes, yes.
Could we lay a little...
a few words before that?
I don't know necessarily that
next time we would do that,
but it would come naturally.
I've been listening to what you've been saying
and it has occurred to me that
if one is responsible
and care is continuous with that,
one would not fear,
one could not fear.
Yes, sir.
Not would not, could not.
Could not fear.
You see, that means really
one must understand fear.
One must understand fear.
Yes.
And also the pursuit of pleasure.
Those two go together,
they are not two separate things.
What I have...
what I've learned here
in our discussion is that
what it is,
if I followed you correctly,
that we should turn ourselves toward understanding
is not what are called values.
Oh, no.
We don't understand love,
we understand all those things
which we catch ourselves into...
Which I don't know.
...that militate against any possibility whatsoever.
This is what's so hard to hear,
that to be told that there just is no possibility.
This produces immense terror.
Do you think next time
when we converse together
we could begin at that point
where we could discuss fear?
Oh, yes.
Good.
But, sir, before we enter fear,
there is something which we should discuss very carefully.
What is order in freedom?
Fine. Fine. Yes. Yes.
How thaw theour bodies
until they accept the dispom HTV
and accept their negative siempre